またそんな顔して 唇噛み締めて
mata sonna kao wo shite
There you go, making that face again,
biting onto your lips.
kuchibiru kamishimete
弱さを隠してるけど
yowasa wo kakushiteru kedo
You're hiding your weak side,
sono hitomi no oku
but deep in those eyes,
その瞳の奥 うずくまる君が
uzukumaru kimi ga
I can see you cowering.
本当の心なら
honto no kokoro nara
If you had a true heart,
思って 泣いて 一人で 不安で
omotte, naite, hito yonde, fuwande
you would care, cry, call for someone and worry.
なんで 痛いの 持ってんだ
nande itai no mottenda
Why are you holding onto the pain?
僕に そっと 預けてよ
boku ni sotto azukete yo
Share some of it with me.
直ぐじゃ無理と思うのならば
sugu ja muri to omou no naraba
If you don't think it's possible right away,
少しずつでいい
sukoshi zutsu de ii
you can do it slowly, bit by bit.
翼の無い僕等はきっと
tsubasa no nai bokura kitto
We don't have wings,
tobenai toki mitsuketeru dake
but I'm sure we're only finding times that we can't fly.
飛べないと 決め付けてるだけ
koe no kagiri kimi wo yobu yo
I'll call for you to the limits of my voice
声の限り君を呼ぶよ 迷わないように
mayowanai you ni
so that you won't get lost.
フワリ心舞い上がれ あの風に乗せて
fuwari kokoro maiagare
Soar up to the sky with your gentle heart,
ano kaze ni nosete issei erose
ride on that wind, and get it all at once.
Natsume
Yuujinchou
Got you!
もらった
Nyanko's Book of Boredom
Damn, how could someone as graceful as myself have done that?
いかん 美しい私としたことが にゃん
Kyaa!
"Kyaa?"
A white piglet fell!
白い子豚が落ちて来た
な 何だと
What'd you say? This is why I hate inferior animals.
これだから 下等動物は
あれ
It's actually a kitty, now that I look carefully.
よく見たら猫ちゃんだ
猫ちゃん 大丈夫
Are you okay, kitty?
Did you fall down like me?
私みたいに落っこっちゃったの
あ あんな所まで登れない
I can't climb up there.
What should I do?
どうしよう
Who cares about that! How dare you call me a piglet?
そんなことよりもよくもこの私を豚呼ばわりしてくれたな
How cute!
可愛い
In the first place, this is just a temporary form.
そもそもこのスタイルは仮の姿
My true form is much more grand!
本来の私は高貴な姿なのだ
きゃじゃない
Don't laugh at me! Damn human children.
これだから 人の子は
I'm really glad, though.
でもよかった
猫ちゃんに怪我がなくて
You aren't injured at all.
No, no, I can't stay with her.
いかんいかん 付き合っていられるか
I have to climb out of here right away.
さっさとこんなとこ 登って
Wait, kitty! Don't go!
待って 猫ちゃん 行っちゃ嫌だ
一人にしないで
Don't leave me alone!
Geez, this is why I hate human children.
全く これだから人の子は
Kitty...
猫ちゃん
You sort of... smell strongly of sake.
猫ちゃん なんかお酒臭い
I'm back!
ただいま
変ね
ただいま 塔子さん
I'm back, Touko-san.
お帰りなさい
Welcome back.
I'm going to go change.
着替えてきます
Okay.
Is something wrong?
どうかしましたか
Yeah, you see...
うん それがね
うむ なるほど
I see.
The recession is just as bad.
相変わらずの不景気だ
The stocks are...
株の点きが
Sensei!
先生
Touko-san said the shrimp in the fridge are gone.
冷蔵庫のエビが無くなってるって 塔子さんが
Oh? Well, that's quite odd.
お それは珍妙な
You ate them, didn't you?
食べただろう 先生
What?
何
家の人に迷惑かけるなって あれほど言ってるのに
I told you so many times not to bother the other people in this house.
愚か者 この私を疑うのか
Fool! Are you doubting me?
当然だ
Of course.
私は知らんぞ
It's got nothing to do with me.
第一 エビの一匹や十三匹で うだうだ言うな
Besides, don't make such a big fuss over one or thirteen shrimp, you ignorant boy!
この愚民めが
This is the CD I borrowed from Nishimura.
これ 西村に借りていたCDだぞ
What are you going to do about it?
どうしてくれるんだ
It's your fault for leaving it there, idio-
そんなとこに置いとく方が悪いんだ
So it was you!
やっぱり
Get out!
出てけ
ふん お前には愛想が尽きた
I'm tired of being with you!
Natsume, you damn punked-out, baldy, white asparagus!
夏目の不良 はげ 白アスパラ
Takashi-kun, I heard a big sound!
貴志君 大きな声がしたけど
Sorry, it was nothing!
すいません 何でもありません
Natsume, you damn punked-out, baldy, white asparagus!
夏目の不良 はげ 白アスパラ
ふん 夏目の阿呆め
Stupid Natsume.
Still, that fat cat is a real bother.
しっかしあの白豚猫にも困ったもんだ
He comes here every night and drinks like crazy.
毎晩のようにこの八ッ原に来ては 大酒をかっくらってくんだからな
Drinks, drinks.
飲む飲む
And it's not just sake! He eats boatloads!
酒だけじゃないぞ 食べる量も半端じゃない
食べる食べる
Eats, eats.
He sings too.
歌も歌うぞ
Tone-deaf, tone-deaf.
音痴音痴
He's a bad drunk, too.
酒癖は悪いし
That's right! He goes wild after he drinks.
そう 飲んだら必ず暴れるし
Drunken frenzy, drunken frenzy.
酒乱酒乱
So, what are we going to do?
で どうする
うーん 確かに夏目殿はこの八ッ原の恩人で
It's true that Natsume-dono is this Eight Field's savior,
but we need to watch out for that big-eating, tone-deaf, drunken cat.
大食いで酒乱で音痴の豚猫はその用心棒だ
But, still! There's a limit to how much we can take!
とはいえ 我々の我慢にも限度がある
Right, right.
よーし 八ッ原の平和のため
All right, for the peace of the Eight Fields,
we'll make that big-eating, tone-deaf, drunken, old cat pay double!
あの大食いで酒乱で音痴の加齢臭の豚猫をボイコットするぞ
Double, double!
増えた増えた
我々は八ッ原の平和のため
For the peace of the Eight Fields, we'll make that big-eating, tone-deaf, drunken, old cat pay double!
あの大食いで酒乱で音痴の加齢臭の豚猫をボイコットするぞ
Bravo!
ブラボー
Ma-Madara-sama!
ま 斑様
どうせそうだろうよ
That's right.
I'm a big eater,
大食いで
a bad drunk,
酒乱で
tone-deaf,
音痴で
and old!
加齢臭で
I eat thirteen shrimps from the fridge,
冷蔵庫のエビ十三匹は食うし
and I'm bad with CDs!
CDは割るし
成敗
Take this!
A, B, C, D?
Note: A, B sounds like ebi (shrimp) and C, D for CD.
AB CD
E, F, G...
EFG
Hey, you there, monk.
やい 坊主
どなたかな
Who are you?
八ッ原をお祓いしておけ
Exorcise the Eight Fields.
That place is a den for ungrateful Ayakashi.
あそこは恩知らずなあやかし達の巣窟だ
二度と居着けないようにお清めするんだ
You should purify them so that they won't go wild.
Thoroughly and completely.
徹底的にな
あ ちょっと待ちなさい キミ
Hold it.
I'm back, dad.
父さん
ただいま
Ah, welcome back.
ああ お帰り
I just felt something strange.
あ 今妙な悪寒が
Hey, what should we do after this?
な どうするよ この後
帰るよ 宿題 あるし
Go home, we've got homework.
Ah, that's right.
あ そっか
It's so hot.
暑いな （暑い）
Mareina.
あれいいな
It's expensive.
高いだろう
I bought it.
買っちゃった
I haven't seen that uniform before.
見かけない制服だな
Which school is it from?
どこの学校だ
Not sure.
さあ
Hey, wait.
おい おい
Hey, which school are you from?
ねえ キミ どこの学校
Oh, it's you two.
なんだ お前達か
夏目のクラスメイトだろう
You're Natsume's classmates, right?
あ 何だ
Oh, you're his friend.
夏目の友達なんだ
友達
Friend?
No, I'm his sensei.
違う 私はあいつの先生だ
先生
Sensei?
We just broke up, though.
たった今 その縁を切って来たところだがな
お前ら ちょっと付き合え
You two! Come with me for a bit.
How much do you have?
お前 いくら持ってる
I used a lot at the arcade.
ゲーセンでだいぶ使ったからな
Hey.
おい
Order another mixed pizza and a gratin.
ミックスピザおかわり 後グラタンも
You're still going to eat?
まだ食べるの
いくらなんでも 食べ過ぎじゃ
Aren't you eating a bit too much?
Don't worry, eating a lot is good for you.
心配するな 腹は至って健康だ
No, the problem is that it's not good for our wallets.
あ いや 病弱なのは俺たちの財布の方で
What?
なに
いや
No, nothing.
別に
By the way, what's an arcade?
ところで ゲーセンってのは何だ
煎餅の一種か
A type of rice cracker?
Here's your hotdog.
ホットドッグ お待たせしました
Thanks, I'd like a pizza and gratin too.
おお 後ピザとグラタンな
ええと あ
Geez, what a waste of money.
やれやれ とんだ散財だ
Hey, you.
ねえ キミ
Sensei.
先生
ねえ 先生
Hey, sensei.
We kind of want to go home now.
僕たちそろそろ帰りたいんですけど
Please, sensei.
頼むよ 先生
おい おいおいおいおい
Damnit!
何 くそ
行け行け行け行け行け行け
Go, go, go!
We sure caught a weird one.
変なのに捕まっちゃったな
お やった!
Yes!
抜いた ひょー
I haven't seen the cat today.
今日は猫ちゃんが見えないわね
Do you know where he is, Takashi-kun?
貴志君知らない
さあ
Not sure.
I wonder if Nyankichi-kun is hungry?
お腹空かしてないかしら ニャン吉君
Nyankichi?
ニャン吉
Oh? That's strange.
お 珍しいな
キミの猫だよ
Your cat.
いつも私の座布団にでんと居座っているのに
He's always sitting imposingly on my seat.
Ah, sorry.
あ すいません
でもいないと寂しいもんだな ニャン五郎も
It's kind of lonely without Nyangoro around, though.
N-Nyangoro?
ニャ ニャン五郎ですか
It's kind of surprising Nyanko-sensei got so close to them.
意外と藤原家に馴染んでいたんだな ニャンコ先生
What are you doing there?
なにやってんだ こんな所で
Just keep on regretting it, kid.
反省しろ 未熟者め
Like heck I'd go back to you now.
当分帰ってやるもんか
The cat... smiled?
猫が 笑った
Nishimura.
西村 これ 借りてたCD
Here's the CD I borrowed.
夏目
Natsume.
Who was that?
誰だよ あれ
誰って
Who?
The girl, man.
女子だよ 女子
The girl?
女子
Yeah, that's right.
そう 喫茶店のメニューを上から下までぺろりと平らげる女子
The girl that ate everything on the menu from top to bottom.
She even made us go to the arcade with her.
おまけにゲーセンまで付き合わされて
She just wouldn't let us go home.
帰らせてくれないんだぜ
And thanks to her, my allowance for this month is completely gone.
おかげで今月の小遣い全部パーだ パー
Completely gone!
I don't know any girls like that.
知らないぞ そんな女の子
She knew you, though.
向こうはお前のこと知ってた
She probably has the wrong person.
人違いだよ
第一 俺 女の子の友達なんていないし
I don't have any female friends in the first place.
"Friend?"
友達
"No, I'm his sensei."
違う 私はあいつの先生だ
先生
Sensei?
That's what she said.
そう言ってたぞ
Tell me more about her.
詳しく話してくれ
こら
Hey, you!
校則違反だよ 下校中にゲームセンターだなんて
It's against school rules to go to the arcade on the way home from school.
But, well, it's kind of surprising.
っていうか ちょっと意外
夏目君でもゲームやるんだ
So even you play games, Natsume-kun?
まあ 朝からゴミあさるよりはよっぽど健全だけど
Well, it's healthier than going through the garbage in the mornings.
Onee-chan.
お姉ちゃん
Oh, Tamiko-chan!
あら 民子ちゃん
こんにちは
Hello.
一人
Are you alone?
ううん ママと
No, I'm with my mom.
I see.
そう
She's from my neighbourhood.
近所の子よ
Hello.
こんにちは
Going shopping?
お買い物
うん 明日ピクニックだもん
Yeah, we're going to a picnic tomorrow, after all.
あ 民子ちゃんのパパとママ 一緒にお休み取れたんだ
So your mom and dad both got time off!
That's great.
よかったね
Yeah!
This girl's parents both work...
この子のお家 ご両親が共働きでね
いない
He's gone.
逃げられた
He ran away.
ただいま
I'm back!
Maybe I'll go tease Natsume's friends again.
また夏目の友達でもからかうかな
だれだ
Who's there?
久しぶりだな
It's been a while.
It's me.
俺だよ 俺
That voice... Enkou?
その声は 猿猴か
そうだ
That's right!
What do you want?
何の用だ
何
Well, I heard that you cut ties with the human that holds the Book of Friends.
お前が友人帳を持つ人間と縁を切ったと聞いてな
お前には関わりないことだ
That has nothing to do with you.
Now that you're not related, you wouldn't mind me taking the Book of Friends, right?
縁を切ったのなら
遠慮なく俺が友人帳を頂いても構わん訳だ
Remember, you turned it down,
いいな 断ったぞ
so don't come complaining to me later.
後で文句を言うな
That's it.
それだけだ
I haven't... Wait!
あ ま 待て
What's the meaning of this, Madara?
何のまねだ 斑
I won't let you pass.
ここは通さん
Don't play with me!
ほざけ
You're attached to it, Madara.
未練だぞ 斑
貴様 友人帳が惜しくなったか
You've come to desire the Book of Friends now?
Or... don't tell me you've come to like humans?
それともお前 まさか人間を
Shut up!
黙れ
Natsume, you idiot.
夏目の阿呆はともかく
Anyway, I just can't stand other Ayakashi stealing the Book of Friends.
友人帳がほかの妖に奪われるのは 我慢にならんからな
Don't call me stupid.
Note: The cawing sound crows make sounds like "stupid" in Japanese.
阿呆言うな
You eat a lot for such a small cat.
小さいのによく食うな お前
よせよ くすぐったい
Stop, that tickles!
Wh-What?
にゃ にゃんと
Oh my, it's completely attached to you.
あらあら すっかり貴志君に懐いちゃって
We'll be keeping it while my friend is on his business trip for 2-3 days.
知り合いが出張から戻る二三日の間だ
Sorry, but look after it for me.
すまんが面倒を頼むよ
Sure.
はい
Ah, look, it's like a ball of yarn.
ああ 見て
けっ 何が夏目だ
Who cares about Natsume!
Who cares about the Book of Friends!
何が友人帳だ
Treating me like an idiot...
バカにしよってからに
Shut up!
うっさーい 見るんじゃないぞこら
This isn't some freak show!
Get lost!
ひっこんでおれ
All right, let's sing a song!
よし 歌でもいっちゃおかな これ
The stars are so beautiful!
星が～綺麗だな～
Yeah, the ancient heavens!
天丼のブルース～
あ 昨日飲みすぎた
I drank too much yesterday.
Ah, the water from these rocks...
この岩清水は
あ 頭ずきずきする
My head's ringing...
Ah, shut up!
うざいな もうチュンチュンチュンチュン
そう言えば腹が減ったな
Ah, I'm pretty hungry.
Got you!
もらった
お腹空いたね
You're hungry, huh?
I know, I have some chocolate.
そうだ チョコあるんだよ
Here's half for you, kitty.
はい
猫ちゃんにも半分こ
It's good, huh?
美味しいね
I was supposed to split it three ways with my mom and dad.
本当はパパとママと三分こだったの
でも またピクニックだめになっちゃったから
They said we couldn't go on a picnic again, so I went by myself.
一人できたの
そしたら 落ちちゃった
And then I fell!
Oh yeah, how about you come live with me, kitty?
そうだ 猫ちゃん お家に来ない
We can eat meals and snacks together!
一緒にご飯食べたり おやつ食べたりしようよ
一人じゃなかったら きっとおいしいよ
I'm sure it's a lot more delicious than eating alone!
What is all this?
何だ
ははー 隠れてないで 出て来いよ 先生
Don't hide. Come on out, sensei.
Oh, you did all this?
何だ お前の仕業か
うわ 雨
It's raining!
Oh no! My mom said rabbits die if they get wet!
大変 ママがうさぎは濡れると死んじゃうって言ってた
Will you die too kitty? Huh? Huh?
猫ちゃんも死んじゃうの
ねえ ねえ ねえ
Ah, what should I do? The kitty is going to die!
うわ どうしよう 猫ちゃんが死んじゃう
Calm down, child. That won't happen.
落ち着け 人のこよ それはない
猫ちゃん ごめんね
I'm sorry, kitty.
You said you wanted to go home, but I stopped you!
帰りたいって言ってたのに あたしが止めちゃったから
I'm sorry! You even came to me, kitty!
ごめんね 猫ちゃん残ってくれたのに
猫ちゃんが死んじゃうよ
But you're going to die!
苦しい 死ぬ
It's gotten quiet now.
静かになった
Humans are such fragile creatures.
人はなんと脆弱な生き物だ
I hate weaklings.
弱いものは嫌いなんだ
They're weak, yet they care for others.
弱い癖して 他人を気遣い
They have no powers, yet they desperately try to protect others.
力もないくせに 必死に誰かを守ろうとする
この子も
Just like her.
あいつも
And him.
先生
Sensei!
Nyanko-sensei!
ニャンコ先生
Sensei!
先生
ニャンコ先生
Nyanko-sensei!
Huh? I'm flying.
あれ 飛んでる
What a wonderful dream.
すてきな夢
It's all warm and fuzzy.
温かくて ふわふわだ
あ お嬢ちゃん どうしたんだい
Are you okay, missy?
大丈夫 お嬢ちゃん
Are you okay?
お名前はなんて言うのかな
What's your name?
Sensei!
先生
おい 先生
Sensei!
ニャンコ先生 どこだ
Nyanko-sensei! Where are you?
しょうがない
Geez...
Natsume!
夏目
色づく 西空に
hi no tsukurishi zora ni
On that day where the sky was ablaze,
差し込む一筋の陽
sashikomu hitosuji no hi
and rays of light were piercing through,
yuudachi no ameagari ni
the evening rain had stopped,
夕立の雨上がりに
気付く夏の匂い
kizuku natsu no nioi
I noticed the scent of summer,
ひしめく光が照らす
hishimeku hikari ga terasu
and the crowded, shining lights.
想いに耳を澄ませば
omoi ni mimi wo sumaseba
If I turned my ear to my thoughts,
聴こえし友の面影
kikoeshi tomo no omokage
I could hear traces of my dear friends.
夏夕空 薫り立つ
natsu yuuzora kawarirazu
The summer evening sky
鮮やかな過ぎ去りし日々
azayaka na sugisarishi hibi
and the vivid passing days were just the same,
心のまま笑いあった
kokoro no mama warai atta
and so I laughed; it was just like
あの夏の思い出よ
ano natsu no omoide yo
my memory of that summer.
Next Time on
Natsume Yuujinchou
Five Day Mark
Sensei touched my mark and he became small!
俺の痣に触ったら 先生がちっこくなった
Yes, it's the effect of the curse you picked up.
ああ あんたが拾ってきた呪いの影響さ
You're Hinoe?
お前は丙
It's the five day mark curse.
五日印の呪い
You only have five days left to live, Natsume.
夏目 あんたの命はあと五日だよ
Five?!
いつか？